Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1800-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of albums
circa 1800-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920)
New-York Historical Society
PR 2
20 Linear feet (circa 562 volumes)
The Album Collection (formerly referred to as the Album File) consists of published and unpublished volumes and scrapbooks acquired from various sources. Styles of albums vary from manufactured carte-de-visite albums to scrapbooks made by pasting images and clippings into accounting ledgers, and fine presentation albums with leather or velvet covers and ornate metal clasps. Albums were created to document families, places, or events, or to honor a person's career. Some volumes included in the file are published works documenting well know locations or persons. The materials comprising the albums are primarily photographic including tintypes, albumen prints, silver gelatin prints, platinum prints and cyanotypes, but also include clippings, engravings and etchings, drawings and other materials. Various photographers, printmakers, and artists are included in the collection.
Arrangement
Albums are filed sequentially by numbers assigned, initially during the creation of the database that provided access to key information about the albums, and subsequently as albums were accessioned into the collection. Every effort was made to bring together albums related by provenance or in some cases categories or subjects. However, the main shelf arrangement is by size so it was not always possible to place related albums together. Reference is made in the note field of the database to albums related by provenance.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Albums are also kept with other collections, and can be located through the index to the Zinkham Guide. In addition, many print and photograph albums published as books such as Alexander Gardner's Photographic Sketchbook of the Civil War, are in the Library collections. Both the Library and Manuscript Department have many collections that include scrapbooks with pictures and that at times overlap the content of the albums in this collection.
Scope and Contents
Portrait albums make up the bulk of the Album Collection (formerly referred to as the Album File). These include family albums, class albums, and albums depicting celebrities and government officials. Many family albums are included, from early carte-de-visite albums dating to the 1860s, to series of albums depicting the Canoune family from 1892-1929, and the Robert Ludlow Fowler family from 1917 to 1951. Another significant series is the group of albums that had belonged to the Countess Magri, the widow of Tom Thumb, which feature many well-known personalities of the 19th century. Some albums come from well-known people, including the artists J.Q.A. Ward and Joseph Keppler, and the singer Emma Thursby. Other albums document firemen, Civil War regiments and classes of various colleges, including Amherst, Rutgers Institute, Packard Business College and others. Some family albums have clear ethnic associations, such as images made in both Ireland and America, or in Germany and America, and some albums include images of African Americans
Albums documenting geographic locations make up the next largest group of albums. Many depict New York City scenes, including interiors and exteriors of residences, churches, businesses, construction projects, including Grand Central Station, the water system and the George Washington Bridge, and such civic celebrations as the subway opening in Manhattan and the Columbian Quadricentennial Celebration. The file also includes an early album of photographs of San Francisco made in 1856 by George Fardon. Two volumes of early Kodak snapshots record an 1891-1892 tour of western states. Other albums include commercial images of Europe and Cuba that were collected by travelers.
Some albums concentrate on specific subjects. Albums relating to the Civil War include an album by George Barnard depicting Sherman's campaign in the south, a book of 120 cartes-de-visite caricature photographs from the 1860s, and two volumes showing New York monuments at the Gettysburg battlefield. The Spanish American War, and World War I are also each represented by several albums. Another album depicts the harbor defenses in New York during World War II. Among less well-known military actions that are documented in the Album file are the activities of the 1st New York Cavalry during the punitive expedition against Pancho Villa in 1916 and an expedition by the American Asiatic Fleet in Korea in 1871. Albums depicting ships, hunting, fishing and camping, costume balls, picnics, sports such as boxing and fencing, and one depicting the career of Richard I of the Crag, a bull terrier show-dog, are other examples of subjects found in the Album File.
A large number of prominent and not-so-well-known photographers, printmakers and publishers are represented in the Album Collection. Prominent portrait photographers include Mathew Brady, Falk, Sarony, Rockwood, and Man Ray. George P. Hall, Wurts, and Brown Bros. photographed scenes in New York City, and George Fardon, I.W. Taber, and William Henry Jackson photographed in the West. In addition to Civil War images by Brady, there is an album of photographs by George N. Barnard. Talented amateurs include Howard Masten Canoune, Ernest L. Scott (who was a member of the Camera Club of New York), and the artist Edward Willard Deming. The work of etchers and engravers are represented in full length works, including images of World War I by Bernhardt Wall and images of animals by Samuel Howitt.
Most of the volumes in the Album Collection are manufactured albums made specifically to contain photographs: carte-de-visite albums, albums with brittle, black kraft paper pages from the late 19th and early 20th century, and three-hole binders with plastic-covered pages. More expensive albums include tooled leather or velvet covers, and ornate clasps and embellishments. The compilers of some albums were creative in their presentation, embellishing the pages with drawings, poetry and other writing. The photographs in the album are primarily albumen and silver gelatin prints. The albums also include tintypes, cyanotypes, platinum prints, snapshots, clippings, engravings and etchings, drawings, postcards, pamphlets, greeting cards, and other materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Album Collection is made up of volumes from various sources. Some were transferred from Manuscript collections, others were donated directly to the Print Room, and some albums were purchased at auction or from dealers. Some provenance information is included in the finding aid, some is available on request from the reference librarian through reference to an internal database, and other provenance data is unknown.
Separated Material
"Building the George Washington Bridge," previously Album 218, is now part of PR 137, George Washington Bridge Construction Photograph Collection.
"Photographs of the War of the Rebellion," previously album #347, has been made its own collection and is now PR-088.
"Artistic houses: being a series of interior views of a number of the most beautiful and celebrated homes in the United States with a description of the art treasures contained therein," previously album #391, has been made its own collection and is now PR-087.
"Mr. Vanderbilt's house and collections / described by Edward Strahan [pseud.]," previously album #397, has been made its own collection and is now PR-169.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies of the following albums are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Album of photographs of window and store displays, New York City
San Francisco album, 1856
Albums of photographs depicting the construction of Fort Tryon Park, 1930-1935
Photographic record of Work Projects Administration for the City of New York, 1938
Accruals
The collection is open for additional albums to be included over time.
Albumen prints.; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Engravings (prints); Etchings.; Gelatin silver prints.; Group portraits.; Lithographs.; Photograph albums.; Portraits.; Snapshots.; Souvenirs.; Tintypes (prints); Anniversaries.; Armies -- Officers.; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Businessmen -- New York (State) -- New York.; Celebrities -- 19th century.; Dwellings.; Family.; Fire fighters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Interiors.; Legislators -- New York (State); Monuments.; Parades.; Public buildings.; Sherman's March to the Sea.; Students.; Sports -- United States.; Teachers.; Travel.; Universities and colleges.; Water-supply -- New York (State) -- New York.; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Photographs -- 1856.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Photography.; Barnard, George N., 1819-1902; Beato, Felice, 1832-1909; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896; Canoune, Howard Masten; Child, Edmund Bramhall, 1846-1946; Deming, Edwin Willard, 1860-1942; E. & H.T. Anthony (Firm); Fagersteen, Gustavus; Fardon, G. R.; Fowler family; Geo. P. Hall & Son; Gillray, James, 1757-1815; Gottscho-Schleisner, Inc.; Howitt, Samuel, 1765?-1822; Keppler, Udo J., 1872-1956; Low, A. Augustus, 1844-1912; McDonnald & Sterry; Notman Photo Co. (Boston, Mass.); Ray, Man, 1890-1976; Sarony, Napoleon, 1821-1896; Taber, I. West; Ward, John Quincy Adams, 1830-1910; Witteman, A. (Adolph), 1845-1938
- [Album of tintypes of the Walter S. Poor family, Ridgefield, Connecticut], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Small red album measuring 2 x 1 3/4 inched, with gold embossed designs on cover, and filled with gem tintypes of unidentified members of the Walter S. Poor family of Ridgefield, Connecticut
- [Album of gem tintypes belonging to J.S. Warwick], [1865] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 2)
  From the Library of G. Creighton Webb (1853-1948) gift of his niece Mrs. Jorge André; inscribed to J.S. Warwick, Christmas 1865, from his "Auntie Maggie"; 15 unidentified gem tintype portraits of men, women and children
  Abstract
  15 unidentified gem tintype portraits of men, women and children.
- [Album of gem tintypes owned by Marian Ward Canton], 1866 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 3)
  Gem tintypes of men women and children; one image of young woman reading; three African-American or Afro-Caribbean women, wearing scarves, earrings and necklaces.
- [Album of unidentified tintypes of men and women], [1880-1889] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 4)
  Tintypes of men and women, including group portraits of men.
- Portraits of the Presidents of the United States from Washington to Grant, 1873 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 5)
  Published by Edward Fitzki, Washington, D.C.; each president shown with birth and death dates, and terms of office; portraits are round, and attached and folded accordian fashion to a small case, title on one side, embossed image of the White House on the other.
- [Album of gem tintypes], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 6)
  Small album with two gem tintypes on each page; images include men, women and children, one full length view of man wearing long smock; most are unidentified.
- [Album of photographs from a trip by Ed Machurek and Irvin Geier up the Hudson River, to Lake George and Mt. Marcy], [1922] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 7)
- [Album of photographs of Florence N. Levy], 1871-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 8)
  Six photographs depicting Florence N. Levy as a baby in 1871, in 1873, 1877, 1884, 1898, and 1912; album can be folded out and all photos viewed at once
- [Vache-Cox family album], [188--189-] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 9)
  Cabinet cards and cartes-de-visite of men, women and children, including a photograph of a painting of Alexander Vache, M.D.; Lorena Hoffman Gillman; Mayer Lewin; Elias Philips Hoges; Emilie Caroline Henry; a boy with a cricket bat; Clinton Levi Bogg; Rachel Wilson, Florence Monk; Hope Monk; Henry Pilcher; John W. Bernhardt; the ship SS City of Rome. See also Albums 38-40, 100.
- [Album of cartes-de-visite of Union army and navy officers, and] Pres. Johnson and members of the cabinet, [1865] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 10)
- [Churches and chapels of Bronx borough by E. Bramhall Child], [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 11)
  Most images are labeled with name of church and location.
- [Album of photographs of John Rogers and his sculpture groups], [1870-1879] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 12)
  Cartes-de-visite; groups include Sharp Shooters, Country Post Office; Slave Auction; The Village Schoolmaster; Union Refugees; The Picket Guard; The Card Players; Checker Players; The Camp fire; Mail Day. See also Album #85, 315.
- [Album of snapshots in Vermont, New Jersey, Georgia and New York, possibly by Pauline Robinson], 1900-1901 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 13)
  Views of Francis Boyer, "Aunt Nathalie"; a house called Brendon; dogs and cats; gardens; Florham, Madison, New Jersey; Flossie Twombly in wagon; Shelbourne Farms, Vermont: house, training stables, Lake Champlain, Flossie Twombly, Fredenia Webb with tennis rackets; Seward Webb, Watson Webb, including view of Watson Webb on horseback; views on Jekyl Island, Georgia, March 1901, group portraits; Josephine Atterburn; 37th Street (West), The Brick Church; Lucy Gumer [?]; 42 W. 37th Street; Otter Creek; other views.
- Souvenir, Irma Tugini[?], 1901-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 14)
  Snapshots of child in Cairo, 1901, and 1911; views in Nice, including couple and wedding scenes.
- J.P. Marquand, Jr. [Album of cartes-de-visite], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 15)
  "Cartes-de-visite, including sentimental views, celebrities, including Siamese twins, Tom Thumb and wife; a caricature; group portrait of African Americans; portrait of Lincoln and family; State Reform School, Westboro, Mass.
- [Album: cartes-de-visite and tintypes; family photographs and celebrities], [1865] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 16)
  Celebrities include Lincoln, Grant, Tom Thumb and wife; also includes sentimental prints; see also #112, 155.
- Photographs of the construction of the Croton Aqueduct, 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 17.1)
  Views of construction sites, including connecting channel and the dam at Croton Reservoir; the contractor's railroad, cement mixing equipment, steam shovel; men digging; engineers and surveyors with their tools including McCartney, Lowery, O'Meara, Miller, Hopey, Kehoe, McSpedon, Lenehan, Keane, Ruge, Butler, Langley, including view of men in a sleigh; "Lowery's egg factory at Diverting Dam Engr's Office"; scenery in the vicinity including snowy scenes, the Croton Rivers.
  Consists of a main volume, and another volume containing loose photographs.
- Photographs of the construction of the Croton Aqueduct, 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 17.2)
  Loose prints, some duplicates of the album 17.1.
- [Album from the Estate of Ina Love Thursby], [1867--187-] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 18)
  Cartes-de-visite and tintypes of men, women and children, some celebrities, such as Mrs. Tom Thumb; others may be celebrities, or family and friends. See also album #19, 211.
- [Ina Love Thursby album], [1870-1879] (Offsite-box 1, Volume 19)
  From Estate of Ina Love Thursby; some sitters identified, including Ina Love Thursby; some pages inscribed by sitter. See also album #18, 211.
- [Family Album; cartes-de-visite], undated (Offsite-box 1, Volume 20)
  Identified persons include: R. Parish; Mary Jeanette McCurdy Parish; Mrs. Woodhull; C.L. Woodhull; Mr. Thomas Richards, father of Hattie Trumbull; E. Williams; Hattie Roosevelt Trumbull; Parkinson. See also album #138.
- Generals of the Civil War, 1861-1865 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 21)
  Cartes-de-visite of Civil War generals, with identification on the pages below each image.
- City College of New York Class of 1870 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 22)
  Cartes-de visite, tintypes; arranged alphabetically, with statistics compiled by George E. Clay, with place and date of birth, politics, religion, height, weight, intended pursuit and death dates for some of the class; each image signed by the sitter.
- [Joseph Ganoug Cole Family album], 1898-1900 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 23)
  Cole family images, including interiors, and picnic scenes; scenery around Peekskill, at Allaire and Avon, N.J.; Dewey Naval parade and arch; sheep in Prospect Park, Brooklyn; views on President Street, Brooklyn.
- A. Augustus Low, 1867 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 24)
  Views of houses in Brooklyn Heights (and other areas?) and shipping in Brooklyn, including clipper ships. See also album #317.
- Bohn's Pictures of Washington or the Capital illustrated with views of all the public buildings, monuments, and statuary, consisting of thirty national oil paintings. / published by C. Bohn, 103 Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington, D. C., 1874 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 25)
  Capital, including interiors; White House including interior; sculpture of Washington; Washington Monument, the Treasury, Post Office, National Observatory, U.S. Arsenal, U.S. Navy Yard, Smithsonian Institute, City Hall, Military Asylum, Lunatic Asylum, general views of Washington, and Georgetown; Mount Vernon, Washington's Tomb; National Cemetery; canal at Georgetown; lithographs by R. Sachse, Baltimore.
- [MacLaren Family Album], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 26)
  Cartes-de-visite; some sitters identified including Hattie MacLaren, Mary Arnold, Malcolm MacMartin, Harriet MacMartin.
- [MacMartin/MacLaren Family album; cartes-de-visite], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 27)
  Cartes-de-visite, family tree of MacMartin and MacLaren and Richards laid in; drawing of family around dinner table laid in.
- [MacMartin family (and others) Family album], undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume 28)
  Some sitters identified including Harriet MacMartin, Archibald MacMartin, Elizabeth MacMartin, Mary Arnold and others.
- [Reynolds Family album], [1884-1887] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 29)
  Cabinet cards, identified persons include Mrs. George Richards and Marjorie and Harriet Richards as babies and young girls; photographers include Pach Bros., L. Alman, J. Ludovici, A.D. Benedict.
- [Album of photographs of a trip to California], [1905] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 30)
  Views along the railroad in California; homes and friends, beaches, cabins, early automobile, Muir Woods, 17 Mile drive and other locales.
- Graduates of Rutgers Institute, 1863 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 31)
  From the Bella C. Landauer Collection. Two portraits of men [faculty of Rutgers?], 14 portraits of women (graduates of Rutgers); 7 portraits of children; cartes-de-visite and tintypes.
- Album; cartes-de visite and tintypes, undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume 32)
  Unidentified persons, photographers from Tarrytown, NYC, Philadelphia and Munich.
- [De Groot Family album], [186-]-1886 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 33)
  Family cartes-de-visite; tintypes; cartes showing sculpture and paintings, probably from the U.S. Capital. See also #323.
- [Ham and West family album], [1860-187-] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 34)
  Cartes-de-visite and tin types; photographers include M. Brady, Mrs. Moore, Charles D. Fredricks & Co., Grotecloss, and R. A. Lewis; men, including man in uniform, women and children, including child with dog.
- [Album of cartes-de-visite and tintypes], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 2, Volume 35)
  Unidentified album, with images of men, women and children by Brady, Bogardus and others.
- [Album of cartes-de-visite and tintypes of the Allen and Constant Families], 186- [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 36)
  Cartes-de-visite of men, women and children, including Civil War soldiers and officers, and a couple at the window of a prop made to look like a train; copies of prints and paintings; engravings.
- [Album of cartes-de-visite and tintypes with painting mounted on cover], [1867-187-] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 37)
  Painting of peasant woman on cover; "Lena Co[r?]e, Vienna, Apr 2/67" inscribed on fly leaf; a castle, man with boat in foreground; men, women and children, including man with dog, men posing on toboggan; copy of a print showing a skating rink; building perched on a hillside [Italy?]; tintype of Stephen H. Branch; photographers from Montreal, Boston, Gibraltar, Dieppe, San Francisco and other locations.
- [Cox family album], [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 38)
  Cabinet cards and a tintype in a small leather wallet style album; theatrical portrait, group portrait. See also Albums 100, 134, 160, 162.
- [Empty carte-de-visite album], undated (Offsite-box 3, Volume 39)
  See also Albums 100, 134, 161, 162.
- [Cox Family album; cartes-de-visite and tintypes], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 40)
  Includes views of the Cox family, the Lindsay family, the Pilcher family and others; includes hand-colored portraits. See also Albums 134, 160, 161, 162.
- Civil War Officers Photographs, [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 41)
  Officers all identified and most also have the unit to which they belong indicated, including the 3rd Artillery, 12th Infantry and others.
- [McWhorter Family album], undated (Offsite-box 3, Volume 42)
  Cartes-de-visite portraits.
- [Family album: cartes-de-visite and tintypes], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 43)
  Ornate bindings, raised and embossed areas, with white bosses in the corners and on the clasps; some sitters identified, includes Irish and NY photographers.
- [Album of photographs of babies and children], [1869-188-] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 44)
  Primarily cartes-de-visite, also tintypes; some images identified and dated; also includes a portrait of a small dog.
- [Album of cartes-de-visite and clippings], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 45)
  Cartes-de-visite, primarily copies of sentimental pictures, including children, landscape scenes, and clippings of engraved portraits; also includes portraits of man, woman and child.
- [German cartes-de-visite], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 46)
  Portraits of Germans and German-Americans, many made in Germany, some in Philadelphia; many pages have identifications, some of the cards are missing; portrait dated 1863 mounted on fly leaf; clipping of wood engraving showing men conversing mounted on back fly leaf.
- [Album of postcards of Delhi, New York], [1906-1913] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 47)
  50 postcards showing the county seat of Delaware County on the Delaware River: churches, band stand in courthouse park, views along Main Street, School buildings, hotels, waterfall and a covered bridge.
- [A. J. Baker cartes-de-visite album], [186--187-] (Offsite-box 3, Volume 48)
  Views by English photographers, including a castle (possibly Windsor) and photographers in Illinois, Iowa and Ohio.
- [Carte-de-visite album with sentimental pictures and views of Switzerland], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 4, Volume 49)
  No Subnote Content
- [Acker Album], [1870-1879] (Offsite-box 4, Volume 50)
  Cartes-de visite, including portraits of men and women, a copy of a portrait of Robert Burns; "Grip," the raven of Barnaby Rudge; copy of a print showing a Church in England; a dancer; S.M. Acker, London.
- [Cartes-de-visite album of celebrities], [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 4, Volume 51)
  Inscribed on fly leaf: "Mrs. Howard Townsend"; primarily views of celebrities including copies of photographs of Andrew Jackson, Edgar Allen Poe, Daniel Webster, and J.C. Calhoun, photographs of Bancroft, Agassiz, Morse, Lincoln, Civil War generals and others; also includes what appear to be family or friends of album owner. See also Albums #136, 137, 268, 272, 273.
- [Cartes-de-visite album], [1867-187-] (Offsite-box 4, Volume 52)